Today we're going to make Gelato di
Riso which if you don't know what it is,
is ice cream made with rice so
let's talk a bit more about [Music]
it years ago I had this ice cream gelato Gelato di
Riso in Florence uh I don't know if it originates
there I think history is a bit kind of muddy
regarding this ice cream some say it originated
from France some say Italy and then there are a
few people that think it's China but in reality
although China did probably invent what we know
as ice cream it was a very different thing back
then so we can't really claim that that's even
vaguely true but what is gelato deiso gelato ice
cream generalized it just means Frozen and Riso is
rice so what what it is is Arborio rice which is
Italian short grain rice, soaked, cooked and then
the resulting rice is soft, it's then added into a
white based gelato. White base is just basically
an unflavored base so it's pretty easy to do and
you're unlikely to have tried this so we're going
to do this in a couple of stages we need to clean
the rice to get a lot of the starch off then we
need to cook it and then we'll start working on
our ice cream base I'm not using eggs in here I
I know some of you might have a hissy fit about
that I don't like using that many eggs in ice
cream I find it a waste especially when we are
a science-based ice cream Channel and we can use
stabilizers to do the same thing so first stage
get our rice and here we have 75 G of aboro
rice and we are going to wash that in a fine
mesh strainer SL siiv man there's a lot of s's
in there and go on to stage two with our rice
strained what we're doing is trying to get that
layer of starch off the top there are dozens of
ways to make this essentially it doesn't really
matter which order you make this the result is
going to be pretty much the same I'm going to tell
you how I was taught how to make it if you want
to change it up then that's completely fine so
with our rice ready we're going to take our cream
and I'm going to use my heart-shaped spoon
which came from Italy and we're just going
to stir that together make sure there's no
rice stuck to the bottom and we're going
to put that on a gentle heat so simmer it
for about 30 minutes and we will now look
at the next stage and then next stage is our
milk is going to go in the pan get a bigger
whisk and into that we've got to add a few
more ingredients we are going to add one
of two optional ingredients here skin milk powder
so this is z or 0.1% milk F professional icecream
makers use this a lot so we're going to put
that milk powder in this just increases s
makes it a bit smoother a little bit more creamy
mouth feel lots of Pros to using that so the next
stage is a small whisk the next stage is with your
small whisk is our sugar we have we have 180 g of
sugar and 5 G of our stabilizer blend this is
a proprietary blend use whatever stabilizer
you have if you're going to use something like
guag gum or zanan gum bring it down don't use
5 G use something like 2 and 1/2 G G maybe
3 G otherwise it'll be too much so with our
stabilizer and our sugar just going to combine
them quickly and pour that into this mixture and
we can combine that together before go it goes
on heat all right and here we have glucose syrup
it's 40 de a de stands for dextrose equivalent
so this is 40% of the sweetness of all right
if you don't want to use this you can't
get this don't want to buy this then you
can substitute it for straight corn syrup it
won't be exactly the same but it will get you
in the same ballpark if you don't want to use
corn syrup just add the same amount of weight
in Sugar again it's not going to give you the
same result but it will be close all right so
into that we need 60 G all right I'm going to
be a heathen and use this 1/4 cup measurement
if you go with the glucose the 40D glucose it's
sticky stuff all right so I'm going to just going
to leave both of these in the pan I mean look
until this starts to warm up so let's get this
on the hob and warm it up nice and gently so we
got a couple of things going on the heat here this
is our white base if you want to call it that
and we're just heating this up here we've got
stabilizers it needs to go up to 85 see so that's
what we're doing with this part get the heat nice
and hot we can do that because we're not using
eggs get it up to heat as fast as we can stirring
it periodically and over here we have our rice
the heat is just going down and down and down
just Stir It periodically it's starting to Bubble
Up because the water is being evaporated from our
cream it's making the cream more fat heavy so we
started with 35% cream as we're boiling off the
water it's uh reducing slightly but actually we're
we're just trying to cook this AR boreo rice now
it's been on for about 20 minutes I'm going to
turn the heat off and then just leave it there
to chill out for the next 10 minutes right now
our milk mix sure is up to temperature we are
simply going to take our rice and cream add that
in make a mess and we are going to leave this
here to settle down for 15 minutes off the heat
so after we've done that we're going to take a
bowl and we're going to put our mix in there cuz
we need to chill it down make sure you get all
those bits of rice in there cuz this is like the
the essential part and make sure you get the right
size lid you can either chill it down quickly in
a nice bath or put it in the refrigerator over
night once that's completely chilled down we're
going to add in 15 G of vanilla bean paste you
can use vanilla extract if you want but make it a
nice quality one cuz that flavor is subtle and we
need that to be really really delicious then into
your ice cream machine it goes get it churned and
get it dished up and then when you're ready pop it
straight in the freezer for a good few hours after
it's hardened off somewhat we can take it out
of the freezer and get some scooped up into a b
we're going to do a nice close-up shot here and
you can see how delicious that looks super creamy
little Flex of vanilla seeds poking out there
man I'm looking forward to trying this gelato
Deo rice gelato you can see all the little Flex
of or pieces of rice it's not Flex it's whole
pieces of rice it's got a wonderful scoping
texture not too hard not too soft just so
it's got such a subtle smell of that vanilla bean
paste let's try some and see if it's as good as I
remember it's so good the
aboro rice swells up beauti
you got to make sure you cook it got to got
to make sure you cook it don't cook this to
you know an Al Dente kind of stage make sure
it's cooked so it's softened if if you leave
this Al Dente the rice will be too hard the rice
being fully cooked then freezes properly and you
get these almost hard pieces of rice throughout I
Bor Oro rice is very very different to long grain
rice and just that touch of vanilla just makes it
tastes like this Frankenstein between ice
cream and rice pudding man this brings back
memories such a clean flavor such a unique
ice cream I had it in Florence years years
ago uh I'm sure you can probably get it
elsewhere within Italy I've never seen it
outside of Florence if you've had rice gelato
gelato de then let me know whereabouts in the
world did you have it you must try and make
this it's so so good anyway thanks very much
for watching hope you enjoyed this unique
Italian gelato a very traditional one too
don't forget to like And subscribe
I'll see you next time [Music]